Matilda Cruz was 23.
She'd been missing for two weeks
when her body was found
at a county waste facility.
We believe that Matilda
met her killer online
in a chat room dedicated
to lovers of Shakespeare.
We would ask anybody
who uses that chat room
or similar sites
to please contact the CBI
if they come across
any suspicious activity online.
And now Gary Philo,
CEO Of Phiz Systems
and Matilda's boss,
would like to say a few words.
[camera shutters clicking]
Thank you.
I'll be brief.
Matilda Cruz
was a beautiful young soul..
...and a treasured member
of our family here at Phiz.
And that is why
I am offering $10 million..
...for information leading
to the arrest of her killer.
Matilda deserves justice,
and she will get it.
Questions?
Wainright needs us.
Super urgent.
He won't say why.
Interesting,
but I can't go yet.
It's a press conference.
Let's go.
I need one minute.
Naturally, we are
all deeply upset
'and saddened at this tragedy.'
We will get through this.
'We will come back
stronger than ever.'
For Matilda's sake.
Mr. Philo uh, Gary,
what was your personal
impression of Matilda Cruz?
[clears throat]
Well, as with all our employees
she and I had a nice chat
when she first joined us
but beyond that, I never
had the privilege
of getting to
know her personally.
- Come on. Let's go.
- I have 30 more seconds.
Sir, you're a-a famously
thrifty man, aren't you?
Uh, the no-brand sneakers
the compact cars, all that.
Excuse me, I don't mean
to be authoritarian--
Then don't be. We're
investigating a murder here.
Are you thrifty or not?
What in the devil does my
thrift have to do with...that?
Ah. You notice
that tiny little beat
you took before you said "that"?
That, my friend,
was a solid-gold tell.
- What?
- Never mind. You're thrifty.
You're a legendary
cheapskate, in fact.
And yet, you put up $10 million
of your own precious money
to find Matilda's killer.
Why would you do that?
Why?
Because you know for sure
you'll never pay
one single penny of that money
because it's you.
You're Matilda's killer.
Ooh! Aah!
Uh, that's assault.
Lisbon, arrest him!
Stay there.
[theme music]
Ah. Thank you for
getting in here so promptly.
The FBI needs our help.
Agent Darcy.
We just caught a homicide
where the family of the
victim has statehouse juice.
The lieutenant governor has
specifically requested you
for the task force.
He wants the best
on this one, he says.
Whoa. Well, I'm flattered.
Uh, but we already have a case.
A big case.
Yes. So I've heard.
We don't need the team.
Just Jane.
That is, of course,
if you're willing.
Well, I'm...happy to help
I just-as long as
it's okay with you.
'Cause last we spoke,
we weren't exactly
seeing things eye to eye.
The Red John case, you mean.
Yes, it is a mystery, isn't it?
It's not surprising
we have different takes
but that doesn't mean we can't
work together, does it?
Excellent.
It's all settled then.
I know what you're gonna say.
You're gonna warn me
that Agent Darcy's
playing games with me.
She's trying to investigate me
on the sly, bless her heart.
Well, yes, exactly.
Well, I play games
better than she does
so I'm looking forward to it.
Oh, so you get to go
off and have fun
while we deal with
the Philo mess you've left us?
- I'm pretty sure he's guilty.
- Oh, thanks a lot.
I'd love to stick around
and help you solve this crime
but I can't really
say "no" to the FBI.
You know, Darcy
would leave you alone
if you just told
her the truth.
Which truth
you are talking about?
That you didn't kill Red John
that you lied about it
that you did a lot of stupid
things to cover up the lies
and that now he's back, and
you're very sorry, that truth.
- Eh.
- Can't you see.
Your stubborn arrogance is gonna
bite you in the...Agent Darcy.
We gotta get rolling,
they're keeping
the crime scene intact
until we get there.
Okay. I'm ready.
Thanks for lending him to me.
My pleasure.
Glad to see the back of him.
Oh, okay.
- Well, bye.
- Bye. Just go and have fun.
I'm gonna have a great time.
There's my back. See you.
[sighs]
Hey, boss.
Philo's lawyer's arrived
he wants to talk.
What are you gonna do?
Probably gonna
have to let him go.
[sighs]
Ah.
Here she is.
This is the fool
that arrested me.
I am sorry, sir. I under--
I want this little bitch
toasted like a marshmallow.
You'll excuse
my client's anger.
He has every reason
to feel aggrieved.
'His arrest was
an outrageous abuse of power'
I will be brief, counselor..
...You committed an assault.
We can hold you for 48 hours
without charging you
and we will hold you
for those 48 hours.
Unless, of course you would like
to confess
to the murder of Matilda Cruz
in which case, things would
move a lot more quickly.
Agent Lisbon, this is no way
to treat a man
of Mr. Philo's stand--
'Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.'
She can legally
hold me that long?
Yes, but that doesn't mean--
Don't waste your breath.
[sighs]
You may go.
What?
I'm not gonna pay you $1,000
to hold my hand
while this idiotic girl
acts out her hatred of powerful
father figures. Just go!
As you wish, Mr. Philo.
Yeah.
[telephone ringing]
That creep is a
psychopath, and he's guilty
and we are gonna
make him say so.
He cracked once already
when he hit Jane.
Let's make him crack again.
Okay.
[Darcy]
'Victim was found
early this morning'
'by state park rangers.'
'Victim's name is Kati Bauer.
27, married, one child.'
Multiple stab wounds.
Uh, evidence of sexual assault.
Lieutenant Franklin, is this
exactly how you found the body?
[sighs]
Yes, ma'am. I..
...I-I noticed her car
parked off the road.
It looked like it had
been there overnight, so..
...so I and a couple of my men
took a look around and..
...found the poor woman here.
She looks peaceful.
No signs of struggle.
No defense wounds.
Do you know her?
Was she a local girl?
Uh, Santa Carla,
in the valley, but, uh, no.
No, I didn't know her.
This..
...you see, this
is my first homicide.
Just, it's-it's sad.
Mm.
Wine.
[female #1]
'Wine?'
Wine?
Why is that...Kati, would
drink wine on occasion.
Why is that relevant?
Well, it's probably not.
Um, I'm sorry.
I wasn't listening earlier.
You're her in-laws,
you're not her parents
and this is...
this isn't your house?
We live in Pasadena.
This is Sandy and Kati's house.
Sandy is our son,
her husband.
He's on his way home now
from our New York offices.
When did you last see Kati?
Yesterday morning at 9:00 a.m.
We came to take Megan to our
house for the day and give Kati
a little "me" time.
It's a regular thing
we do.
What does Kati like to do
during her "me" time?
'You know,
I think she just likes'
'to give the help the day off'
and enjoys the solitude
and the peace and quiet.
[Darcy]
'And when did you return here?'
Well, it's all a blur, but it
must have been just before 5:00
because I...do my insulin
shot regularly at that time
and I had to hurry
in order to...do it.
And she was gone.
[beeps]
We waited for two hours
and then we called the police.
Did Kati like to
go up to the mountains a lot?
No.
I mean,
perhaps with Sandy, but..
'...on her own, on a whim, no.'
Kati was very much
a creature of habit.
[cell phone rings]
Oh. It's the house phone.
That's odd.
Sorry. That's-that's me.
I just, uh...I like to fiddle.
Don't mind me. Carry on.
- So, Mrs. Bauer, you were say--
- '"New York offices," huh?'
What business
are you and your son in?
We are a design consultancy
for the financial--
Hi. Uh, what kind of
place do you have there?
Uh-huh.
Ah. Oh, interesting. Okay.
No, no, no, no.
Thank you. Bye.
[beep]
Kitchen.
[instrumental music]
[music continues]
Only two outgoing calls
on the landline yesterday
one to you, Shirley--
may I call you "Shirley"?
'At around 8:15 in the morning'
and one call to
Mama Sylvia's pizzeria, 12:07.
Which is strange 'cause
there's no pizza box here.
Well, maybe it was a misdial.
Of course.
Probably is that.
A misdial.
[door closes]
[Male #1]
'Hello?'
Oh.
Mom? Dad?
Sandy. Nice to meet you.
I'm very sorry for your loss.
Oh, darling. Oh.
These people are here
to investigate the, um..
'...the murder.'
Graciella's with Megan.
She's fine.
Oh.
I can't believe
this is happening to me.
Mr. Bauer,
I'm Agent Darcy, FBI.
I'm gonna have to
ask you a couple questions
if you don't mind.
Did you just get
in from New York?
Yes.
Do you recall
your flight number?
We have a jet...
well, a fractional share.
Sweet.
What time did you land?
Thirty-five minutes ago.
Mr. Bauer, we have to
explore all possibilities.
Sandy, how long have you
and Kati been married?
Uh..
...three years, near enough.
Okay. Tell me about her.
I don't know.
What can you say
about a person?
Show them the clip
on the phone, the song.
♪ That horse
and bull falls over ♪
[Shirley]
'That's Kati.
She was an angel.'
♪ Mama's gonna buy you
a dog named Rover ♪
♪ And if that dog
named Rover won't bark ♪
♪ Mama's gonna buy you
a horse and cart ♪
♪ and if that horse ♪♪
Okay, thanks,
yeah, he's a possibility
but can he overcome his natural
passivity to commit murder?
I don't know.
We have some other
important leads to follow.
Sir, your manner
is deeply inappropriate.
I assure you, Mr. Bauer
- This won't be how we'll--
- Yes, yes.
Uh, Franklin, will you
smooth things over here?
Uh, Darcy and I need to go.
If I may just say
so I'm so very deeply
sorry for your loss,
and I, uh...sorry.
If there's anything
I can do for you all
please don't hesitate to ask.
[indistinct conversations]
Alright,people.
What have we got?
ME says petechial hemorrhaging
indicates death by asphyxia.
The hyoid's intact,
so we're probably looking
at a smothering
rather than a strangulation.
'That's all she wrote.
Blood work's clean.'
Decayed state of the body
means there's no way
to get any useful DNA.
No crime scene, no forensics.
Matilda's unknown
chat room buddy
was definitely the last person
to communicate with her.
I followed
the internet trail he left.
It bounces around
the globe then dead-ends
at a pirate server in Macao.
There's no way
to trace our mystery
Shakespeare fan any further.
Matilda's colleagues at Phiz
didn't know very much about her.
Her close friends and family are
all back east in Philadelphia.
She never spoke about
her online life or dating.
Just family and work stuff.
So we've got zip.
If we can't make
a connection to Philo
maybe we should look elsewhere?
No. No, Philo is all we have.
If we don't bust him,
he busts us.
Let's dig deep into Gary Philo
see if we can get any leverage
medical records,
bank accounts, legal filings.
With zero solid evidence
we're never gonna get
warrants for all that.
See if you can call in
any favors. Improvise.
[male #2]
'"Bauer" "mercer drive". yeah.'
We deliver to them.
What's this about?
Did you deliver
to them yesterday?
[male #2]
'"Bauer," "Bauer"'
Nope. No order.
Somebody there
called you at 12:07.
They didn't order anything.
What's this about?
The woman who made
the call has been murdered.
- Oh.
- Manny. What's wrong?
I'll tell you later, sis.
So.
Manny, tell me.
What-what is it?
There's been a murder.
Oh, my God.
Relax, Lila.
- This a family business?
- Yes.
That's nice. Family's nice.
Does your little
brother James work here also?
Yes, he does.
Is he here now?
No, he's not.
[Jane]
'Lila?'
When James came
back from the army
he was a different
man wasn't he?
Troubled.
How do you..
Hey, uh, Lila.
- Are you okay?
- She's fine, it's all good.
Your brother's full name
is James Barca?
When did you last
see or hear from him?
Uh, yesterday.
He left here at about 12:30,
but nothing since then.
This thing is not him. No way.
What do you think, Lila?
N-no.
There's no way it's him.
But?
It's-it's like you said.
He came back from the army
two years ago, and..
...ever since then,
he's been angry and..
...sad and-and violent
sometimes.
Barroom brawls. No big deal.
But he has blackouts and stuff.
And he quit going
to the doctors
and he self-medicates,
and that only makes it worse--
Lila. He's our brother.
And I love him so much, but he--
Manny, what if he did this?
This is not him. Okay?
A car registered
to a James Barca
just got a parking
ticket this morning
half a block
from the Bauer house.
Oh, my God.
Do you have any idea
where your brother might be?
No. I'm done talking.
If James Barca's
car is at Kati's
then he went to
the murder scene in Kati's car
which was left there.
The question is,
how did he leave?
Either he had an accomplice
with another vehicle
or he left on foot.
Or he's still here.
James!
Come out, come out,
wherever you are!
So, Jane, I need
to ask you a question.
Mm.
You still truly
believe Red John is dead?
I don't truly
believe anything.
That's not answering
the question.
Is this an official inquiry?
Should I have
a lawyer present?
Not unless
you've done something wrong.
Have you?
Don't move. Drop the knife.
No.
I said drop the knife!
Stop moving, or I'll shoot.
James, listen, you keep coming
she's not gonna shoot her dead
like you want her to.
She's just gonna cripple you.
Let go of the knife, James.
You can kill yourself later.
Right now you gotta clean
this mess up with some grace
some dignity.
Give your family
a proper goodbye.
You go out like a soldier.
[Wayne]
'Matilda Cruz
loved Shakespeare.'
What's your favorite
Shakespeare play, Gary?
You will learn in time..
...Wayne..
...to call me "Mr. Philo"..
...as for Shakespeare..
...it's a bunch of English
fruits in tights
running around going..
..."blah-blah,
blah-blah, blah-blah."
Give me a break.
Zero interest, okay?
The idea of me meeting anyone
in a Shakespeare chat room
is beyond ludicrous.
[crickets chirping]
[Darcy]
'Kati called up and
ordered a pizza from you?'
Yes, she did, ma'am.
'And then you went
to her house?'
Yes, ma'am, I did.
And then what happened?
I don't know.
Yeah. Sure.
Look, James, you've got
Kati's blood all over your body.
We found you holding
the knife that killed her.
It's gonna be your DNA
on the rape kit, isn't it?
I'm not denying what I did,
but I don't remember doing it.
I must have blacked out.
When I woke up and she was dead,
and I was covered in her blood
I was crazy scared.
I ran into the woods,
I found a hole
and I crawled in it.
And I thought I'd been hiding
in it for days and days
but this
is only tomorrow, right?
Weird.
Every man and his dog
asks you this question, I bet
how many people did you kill
when you were a soldier?
Eight.
So Kati makes nine?
No. Yes.
No.
No, yes, no.
You went to her house
without a pizza.
That means you must always have
planned to kill her, right?
You're on a mission?
Yes, that's right.
I was on a mission.
Hmm.
You're going down, mister.
You hear me?
You're going down.
I know that, sir.
Thank you.
When did you establish
Phiz Systems, Mr. Philo?
[cell phone rings]
Hello, Jane.
Philo confess?
'Nope. He's tight as a drum.'
He won't even admit
to liking Shakespeare.
It's so frustrating
because it seems like
he's gonna crack at any moment.
If we could just
find his weak spot.
He's a know-all.
Loves to be right.
That's where to hit him.
'Okay.'
'And how are things
going there?'
Well, we have
a suspect in custody.
Looks like our man.
I'm not so sure
he is, though.
Same old Jane.
And how's Darcy?
Oh, she's right here, if you
want to ask her directly.
Mm, no, thanks. But send her
my best wishes.
Okay. Bye.
Lisbon sends her love.
Oh. I doubt that.
Oh?
She doesn't like me very much.
Why would you say that?
Oh, come on. Enough about that.
Why don't you think
this is our man?
Ah, it's just a feeling.
Can't really put
my finger on it.
- I disagree.
- Hmm. Okay.
Case closed, then.
Lovely working with you.
Wait a minute.
The case isn't closed.
We have to wait for
the blood and DNA.
We've gotta
get this right.
Lieutenant governor's
watching it very closely.
The lieutenant governor
doesn't give
a damn about this case.
Quit fooling.
What's the real story here?
Why do you want me
on this case so badly?
Okay. You're right. I lied.
I asked for you on the case
because I need your help.
My job's in jeopardy.
It's...you know,
it's office politics.
I need a win.
But you have a win.
You're confident
James Barca's guilty?
But you're not.
And what if you're right?
Hey. Help me.
Come on. Please.
Stay.
If I stay and I'm right..
...we run this case my way.
I'm here to learn.
[chuckles]
Then I'll stay.
Do you recognize
this item?
No.
Are you sure?
Take a closer look.
- I'm sure.
- No.
Take a really good look.
[sighs]
It's a beautiful
object, isn't it?
- Hmm. Suppose so.
- Yeah.
Restful to look at.
Very..
...restful.
[sniggers]
Wait.
Are you really
trying to hypnotizeme?
- No.
- Yes, you are.
Just checking to see
if you recognize that.
No.
[Gary]
'You were. You were trying
to hypnotize me.'
No. No, I wasn't.
[Susan]
'Before we were so rudely'
'interrupted by James Barca'
I was asking you
about Red John.
Now? When I have
eggs coming?
Well, I can't help it.
I'm an FBI agent.
I like to get at the truth.
Hmm.
I tell you what.
How about I do an old-school
psychic reading on you
and then we'll talk Red John?
You wanna do your act?
Mm, what can I say?
I'm a showman.
Okay.
Do your reading
and then we'll talk.
You have to be
completely honest with me.
Of course.
Happy childhood?
Yes.
Who was your
favorite, mom or dad?
Dad.
Mom showed weakness,
Dad was stronger?
Yeah, I guess.
Stronger how?
I don't know.
Uh, you know. Life.
No. Something more
specific than that.
Something you..
...can't talk about easily.
You have the
confidence of an only child
yet there's sadness also.
You lost somebody.
Everybody's lost somebody.
Yes, but you lost
a sister or a brother.
- Which?
- Sister.
Drowning. It wasn't
anybody's fault.
You blame yourself,
which you know is crazy.
Oh, wow.
You're good. Huh.
That's a neat skill.
So now let's talk
about Red John.
That's why you're
relentless in your work.
Because you're
relentlessly hard on yourself.
You know, you should
cut yourself some slack.
You'd be a lot happier.
Come on. You don't
know anything--
You're lonely
and you're sad
because you lock
down your emotions
which accounts for your
stilted seduction technique.
You're capable
of great passion
if you'd just
let yourself go.
But you won't
not until you redeem yourself
make the wrong things right.
But how can
you hope to do that?
You can't bring
your sister back.
You're on your own.
Deep down inside,
you're a cruel man, aren't you?
Here you go, hon.
[mug clatters]
Ah.
- Susan, wait.
- Seriously, Patrick.
- I'm not interested.
- Oh, never mind that.
I realized what's
bugging me about this case.
Agents.
Have you charged him?
Charged who?
The man you arrested.
Uh, the pizza guy.
Who told you
we'd arrested anyone?
Ah. Of course.
Ranger Franklin.
- I was told in confidence.
- Well.
Never mind who
we have in custody.
We need to look
through your wife's stuff.
Now.
This is her room.
Separate bedrooms, huh?
If you tell me what you're
looking for maybe I can help.
Ooh, I doubt
that very much.
[baby crying]
Excuse me.
What are you looking for?
Uh.
Kati wasn't wearing
her wedding ring.
Yes. You're right.
Maybe James Barca took it.
He didn't have it, did he?
Maybe he threw it away.
Possibly. But why?
More likely, she
wasn't wearing her ring
because she left it at home.
Because that's what people do
when they're having an affair.
Were you and Kati
having an affair?
Oh, come on.
No, ma'am,
we were not.
Oh, James, don't deny
yourselves the truth.
You and Kati were
in love. Or am I wrong?
Was it just a little...fun?
A little lust?
No.
I loved her.
And she loved me.
She was the best thing
that ever happened to me.
Why didn't you
tell us before?
Tell you that
she was cheating? What for?
'I don't wanna make it seem
like she was a bad person.'
'Give her family more grief.'
Well, that's
very considerate of you.
How long were you together?
Six months.
I delivered a pizza one time,
and we got to talking.
She was..
...lonely, and..
...I don't know,
we got along.
She said we must have been
married in a previous life.
Does anyone else
know about the relationship?
No.
Look, James, if you
can prove you were lovers
you might be able
to avoid the death penalty.
I don't want to avoid it.
I killed her.
See, thing is, James.
I'm about to..
...80% sure that
you didn't kill her.
I wish that were true.
We'll see.
[birds chirping]
I found this
in your wife's bedroom.
Make of it what you will
but Mr. Barca is innocent.
Your wife's killer
is still out there.
But the man
confessed, didn't he?
Well, he's just
a messed-up kid, that's all.
I could kick him myself.
The truth was right there.
I missed it
by a hair. A hair.
Brush aside the distractions
and it's just so obvious.
[Sandy]
'What is?
I don't follow you.'
No need. No need.
Leave it to us professionals.
And rest assured, the true
culprit will pay dearly.
Excuse me.
"The true culprit
will pay dearly"?
That a little
too theatrical for you?
Where are we going now?
Right now we're going back
to the forest service office.
- To do what?
- To release James Barca.
And get a search warrant
for his brother Manny.
Manny Barca is your culprit?
What's his motive?
Well, who knows? Maybe he was
in love with Kati too.
Come on. That's not enough.
Sure, it is.
Jane, it's not enough.
Deal was we run
this case my way.
Well, the deal's off.
We're charging
James Barca as soon as
the blood work gets back.
I'm sick and tired
of your antics.
Kati Bauer deserves
better than these
stupid games you're playing.
Oh, don't talk
to me about games.
And you don't care
a damn about Kati Bauer.
- Nor is your job in jeopardy.
- Excuse me?
I'm only here so you can
get a good close-up look at me.
Why would I want to get
a good, close-up look at you?
You tell me.
And quit your play-acting.
'Cause you're really
not very good at it.
Red John is alive,
and you know it.
Well, that's a theory.
It's a fact.
And the only question is,
why would you deny it?
Why would you try
and throw me off the trail?
I realized something.
You're not hunting Red John.
You're protecting him
and that's why you..
...claim he's dead.
That's absurd.
What other conclusion
could I come to?
If you're enemies,
why hasn't he killed you?
Well..
Why hasn't he killed
the people you work with?
I don't know.
Well, if Red John is dead
why are the people
that cross him still dying?
Because he has friends.
He has disciples.
Are you one of them?
Is that why you're
protecting him?
I wasn't protecting him,
I was protecting you.
No, Susan.
You have this all wrong.
Patrick, how can I
believe a word you say?
You won't even admit
that Red John is alive.
Okay. Fine.
I admit that Red John
is still alive.
Why did you deny it?
It was a mistake.
But I am not his friend
nor am I one of his disciples.
I sure hope
you can prove that.
Well, I don't have
to prove anything.
You do.
Well, I guess we have
nothing more to do here.
[Susan]
'Bye, Patrick.'
[Franklin]
'Mr. Jane.'
Ah, Franklin.
Listen, uh, big news.
We're gonna release James Barca
first thing tomorrow morning.
Agent Darcy's
getting a search warrant
for his brother Manny's
house and car.
Holy cow. Why?
No real evidence yet
but we're certain
that Manny is our man.
You wanna help us
execute the search warrants?
- Sure thing.
- Alright.
I'll call you
first thing in the morning.
Hey, Jane.
How's it going?
- I need your help.
- 'My help?'
- What about Darcy?
- 'Uh.'
It didn't work out.
Long story.
Uh, no big deal. I'll tell
you when you get here.
- I'm busy here!
- 'Call me when you're close.'
I have to go. Jane needs me.
You guys are gonna have to
handle this yourselves.
Uh, okay.
[male #3]
'Here's some water.'
Thank you.
Traces of DNA were found
under Matilda's fingernails.
Ah.
Ah, so nowyou're going
to test my DNA
by sampling the saliva
I left on that bottle, huh?
That drink of water's
gonna be pretty expensive.
You're busted.
Do yourself a favor.
Get out ahead of this.
Talk to us.
Well, these days I imagine
an intelligent killer
will be very careful
not to leave DNA
on his or her victim.
Everybody makes mistakes.
[chuckles]
Not the killer
of Matilda Cruz.
Sweetheart, if you ever
want a sample of my DNA
all you gotta do is ask.
[instrumental music]
[car honks]
Okay. What happened
with Darcy?
Um, you're not gonna
ask about the case?
Is it under control?
Yes. I missed you.
- I missed you, too.
- Hmm.
- So what happened?
- We fell out.
- Did you crack the Philo case?
- No, not yet.
- That's it? You fell out?
- Well.
You don't think
I'd tell you? Can we go?
[engine revs]
Now we wait.
Tell me what
happened with Darcy.
Hmm.
[switch clicks]
I'm still here.
Yes. I know.
Please, Jane.
Just tell me what happened.
Okay.
I admitted that
Red John is still alive
just like you wanted me to
and she accused me
of working for him.
What?
She thinks I'm one of
Red John's disciples.
The FBI thinks you're
working with Red John?
Don't look
so serious.
- It's a joke.
- What did you tell her?
I told her to go
ahead and prove it.
- Oh, my god.
- Well, news flash.
I don't work for Red John
so she's wasting her time.
- What did Darcy use as proof?
- Well, sh...nothing.
How could she have any proof?
I can't believe you
haven't cracked Philo yet.
I mean, you guys just can't
manage without me, can you?
Don't try and divert
me with insults!
Okay, what did she say
she was gonna do?
- She didn't.
- And you didn't ask her?
Ah! Look.
[Jane]
Excuse me.
You're both under arrest!
I'm not sure why, but hey.
[clattering]
You knew Kati was having
an affair with James Barca
but you didn't
tell Sandy because, uh..
...he'd want a divorce.
And in California,
that means that Kati would get
half the assets and joint
custody of Megan, like a reward.
Exactly. A reward
for being a slut.
Hon, I thought
we agreed not to talk
till Josh Wagner gets here.
Alright.
When you saw Kati
preparing that picnic lunch
you knew it was for
her regular date with James.
She made potato salad
right in front of me.
As brazen as can be.
And you used
your insulinneedle
to inject a
powerful sedative
horse tranquilizer, probably
into all of the wine bottles of that wine rack.
So that whichever bottle Kati took
your plan would still work.
[Shirley] It was a good plan.
It was a very good plan.
Then why are we here?
Those tiny holes you left
in the wine bottles on the wine
rack that was your downfall.
That, and the shard
of glass that you left
up at the picnic site.
All I needed to do was plant
the word "hairbrush"
in your subconscious.
And bait a trap
with a fake story
to be passed on
by chatty Cathy here.
Whoa. Hey, look.
I had no idea
that I was passing on a--
I was just teasing.
Relax. It's fine.
You did very well.
You did a great job.
In fact, you cracked
the case for us.
And that is exactly
what my report will reflect.
Congratulations.
Well, that's...thank you.
Well, think nothing of it.
You know, your call.
But perhaps you might wanna
release James Barca now.
I'm sure his family
would appreciate it.
- James.
- Oh, my goodness, brother.
Oh! James!
Are you okay?
That's nice.
You did good.
Hmm.
I'll be right back.
Oh. Time to go.
Nope. Uh, um, okay.
Thank you.
Yep.
Agent Darcy.
Come on in.
Congratulations.
Case solved.
Although I understand
Jane may have irritated you
somewhat with his antics.
Hey, all's well
that ends well, though, right?
No. We have a problem.
Oh?
These past two days have
confirmed something for me.
I think Patrick Jane
is a cunning
manipulative sociopath.
Oh.
I think he's working
hand-in-hand with Red John.
Really?
If it's true,
we're taking him down.
And you can help,
or you can go down with him.
I'm sorry to be
so blunt
but that's
the FBI perspective.
You deserve full disclosure.
Yes, I see.
Well, you can count
on my full cooperation.
Sorry to inconvenience
you, Mr. Philo.
I'll sign you out
downstairs.
You start thinking
about a new career, Wayne.
'Cause this one's
all over for you.
Ah. Well met. Well met.
Uh, I was just, uh,
telling your hapless friend here
I am gonna bury
you morons in lawsuits.
You may think
you've won this one
but look at
your hands, Mr. Philo.
They're stained red
with Matilda's blood.
Will all great
"Neptune's waters"
wash that blood
clean from your hand?
No.
It's "Oceans."
"Neptune's oceans."
You're right.
"Macbeth," Act II, scene two.
Shakespeare. You lied
to us, Mr. Philo.
'Why would you lie to us?'
No, no, no,
no, no, no, no.
No, no, no. No.
You need to come talk
to us some more, Gary.
I know. I know.
You don't know
whether to hug me
or to hit me.
- Ugh!
- I--
[instrumental music]
[theme music]